Today on the podcast, I sat down with Dana Syracuse and Josh Bohm, both partners at Paul
Hastings.
In this episode, we discussed some of the legal considerations facing entrepreneurs
in the digital asset ecosystem, and we talked about the outlook for 2025 with the incoming
administration.
I think you'll enjoy this one.
So without further ado, here's my conversation with Dana and Josh.
Matt Walsh and Nick Carter are partners at Castle Island Ventures.
All of these expressed by them or the guests on this podcast are solely their opinions
and do not reflect the opinions of Castle Island Ventures.
The guests and hosts may maintain positions in the assets discussed in this podcast.
You should not treat any opinion expressed by anyone on this podcast as a specific inducement
to make a particular investment or follow a particular strategy, but only as an expression
of their personal opinion.
This podcast is for informational purposes only.
Brought down by bad mortgage investments, Lehman, which has 25,000 employees, will be liquidated.
The federal government loans American International Group AIG $85 billion.
This is a different kind of market and the Fed is asleep.
The federal government is stepping in to stabilize Fannie Mae and Freddie Mac, the
two mortgage giants that have been threatened by the housing crisis.
The Bank of England has pumped 75 billion pounds more into Britain's ailing economy
with a new round of quantitative easing.
You print a couple trillion dollars and all of a sudden people start to worry.
So out of this worry, we have something called the Bitcoin.
Bitcoin.
Well, Dana and Josh, thanks so much for hopping on and recording today.
I think we were originally going to record this before the election and it's a good thing
we didn't because a lot has changed in the industry.
So welcome to the podcast.
Great to be here.
Absolutely.
Why don't we start out with some quick backgrounds and orient people around who's actually talking.
So maybe Dana, why don't we start first with you and what your origin story was in this
industry.
Absolutely.
So Dana Syracuse, I'm a partner of Paul Hastings.
I've been a crypto lawyer, been active in the space since about 2011.
So very early.
I got interested in crypto when I was in government and started hearing about it in podcasts and
reading about it online and this concept of borderless metacurrency for the internet.
It was just really fascinating and the idea that before then there had never been a native
payment layer for the internet was really interesting.
And this was at a time when there wasn't very much activity in the space.
It was barely mentioned in the media.
First New York Times article was in 2011 and in my time at DFS was able to meet a lot of
different crypto entities, was able to help work on the BitLicense and left there in 2015,
went into industry and really pivoted the entire practice into just working with digital
asset companies.
We've worked with many of the major players since then from development of licensing strategies,
obtaining complex bank level charters, helping them add new products, going through the entire
lifecycle of examination, enforcement, M&A, and in some cases helping these entities wind
down.
So really be fortunate enough to see every facet of the industry since the beginning.
That's awesome.
Well, definitely some follow up questions on that one, but maybe before we do, Josh,
I'd love to hear your story and how you got into the space.
Absolutely.
Thanks again for having us on my journey to crypto and fintech.
I'd say I began right out of college.
I joined a boutique in SQL Promontory that worked on financial regulatory consulting.
So I was right in the soup of the financial crisis and got thrown right in to work on
failing bank projects.
I saw a lot of things go wrong and I remember BitLic in 2008 being there showing up on a
Monday for a bank I was working for and they didn't open for business and a lot of people
lost their jobs.
It was a real front row seat to how things didn't work very well.
It made me really interested in understanding more about how the system worked from a legal
perspective and how it didn't work.
So I went back to law school.
I did that and then got back to a Wall Street firm where I was doing banking and securities
work.
And then caught my big break.
That firm brought in the first New York Trust project for a crypto exchange in 2014.
And that's where I met Dana.
He was on the other side over at DFS.
And I thought that was just fascinating.
A couple of big takeaways there.
One was it was really fun just to see how old laws of New York banking law could be applied
to this new tech.
And it was just really interesting stuff to do.
And the second big takeaway and a little bigger picture is this was a time right after the
financial recovery, Doc Frank, banks are getting bigger, tech companies are getting bigger,
governments get bigger.
And here you've got the seeds of this technology that if it were to grow, could really be a
counterweight to those forces of centralization and keep more economic control in the hands
of people.
And I thought that was really meaningful and fascinating stuff and wanted to make a career
of it.
So 10 years on, been fortunate to do that with Dana.
That's awesome.
Dana, I can't imagine what it must have been like to be working on the government side
of this in the early days of this industry.
I think back around what I even thought Bitcoin was back in 2012, 2013.
And we were talking about disrupting credit cards and this is going to be for merchant
payments and things like that.
So the industry itself has evolved so much.
What was it like in those early days just trying to get a handle on what this technology
was?
It was getting a handle on the technology.
And also there wasn't very much to learn by comparison to where we are today.
Going through things like the 51% attack and is that even a possibility and the double
spend problem?
Really just rudimentary questions that today no one even really talks about.
In 2014, you started to see that was when Ethereum came to the fore.
That was when XRP Ripple that was created.
And it was really companies that were entities that were concerned with, is regulation going
to stifle innovation?
And that whole narrative has moved on from where we're concerned about stifling innovation
to we need regulatory clarity in X, Y, and Z component.
Every market cycle winds up being very different and this one is different than all the rest
with institutional buy-in at a level that's never been seen before.
Improving regulatory clarity within the US, New York state, leading a lot of these areas.
UK, EU, the MECA regime, just more market infrastructure that's in place that's allowing
for sustained developer activity and intensifying competitive landscape.
So that's how it's different.
But if you look at where things were prior to 2015, but then also with each of the peak
and valley of the various market cycles, there are so many similarities that we continued
issues that I think you have to keep an eye on.
So yes, right now we have a potentially friendly regulatory regime.
Certainly this was a big topic of the election here in the US.
Friendlier partners in TradFi, but all those parties, the regulators, lawmakers, TradFi,
the industry itself, we all react to headlines and they are very aware of reputation, risk
appetite.
So that's going to keep an eye out for things that could undermine that level of competence.
Everyone's excited about potential new legislation, but these are things that can't be an understatement.
We have an unfunded mandate and need to keep an eye out for how do those new laws, how
do those new regulations wind up being implemented?
We've seen different promises of transformative legislation or regulatory regimes through
the years that either just haven't really come to pass.
Headlines, I think those continue to be the same depending on what channel you tune into
or what you read.
Criminality, price, politics, technology, these are all consistent issues.
One thing that I think the cycle will be the same as those early cycles, you're going
to have companies that are too early or can't find product market fit or meet regulatory
headlines.
So how can you be smart about just understanding that that's going to happen?
There've been lots of successes and those survivors understand the cyclical nature of
all of this and just can't turn a blind eye towards like it's going to repeat itself.
It's never going to go back to those very early days where when I left government and
started working with Josh and went into working with participants, there was a question, is
this thing going to go away?
I don't think we're ever going to go back there.
People said Bitcoin was going to either go to zero or a million.
I think it's more likely to go in that positive direction.
So things are going well, but I think we can't turn a blind eye toward the cyclical nature
of all of it.
Let's just hope that this cycle doesn't end with a cataclysmic centralized exchange below
up like several of the past cycles.
We should be so fortunate, but I guess that feeds into the regulatory and I know that
you guys are working with some of the highest profile companies in the industry and obviously
you can't name them by name, but I would love to just get a sense from you guys around a
snapshot of what the law practice looks like today at Paul Hastings in this industry.
So right now I'd say it's two big buckets.
We do a lot of work with called regulated entities and these are the entities Dana was
talking about.
New York Trust companies, national banks, others that have a bank supervisor, they have
a prudential regulator that's in there examining them and looking after them and those entities
are generally crypto focused and they are engaged with custody activities, exchange
activities.
They also want to roll out new products and services and we help them with that.
So one of the big ones that has been coming up recently is, can we launch a stable coin
out of our entity?
So Dana and I help companies do that and it's a pretty involved process.
First you got to confirm, is it legally permissible to launch a stable coin out of this particular
charter that you have?
Sometimes you got to persuade the regulator of that first, then once you've checked that
box, then you look into what it takes to persuade the regulator you can do that in a safe and
sound way.
By that I mean, do you have anti-money laundering controls, do you have the cyber controls,
so on and so forth?
And you submit all that stuff and then if you're successful you get that approval at
the end of the line.
Another big bucket of the practice are what we would call the entities that are trying
to still be tech companies and not be regulated entities.
Those companies, they're the staking service providers, non-custodial wallet providers,
some companies that are launching network tokens in a way that's intended just to be
done for use and not as a capital raising instrument.
So for those, the approach is a little different.
We first want to help them develop a roadmap and analysis to say, hey, do you have a real
sound basis for saying you shouldn't be regulated and if so, what are the guardrails you want
to put around that and how do you make sure that you have coverage across the waterfront,
across your marketing channels, your contracts, et cetera, to defend and be consistent with
that position?
The data I also do will go in if the client wants in those cases and do no names calls
with regulators, sometimes even go in and try to get no action relief with regulators.
In the prior Trump administration, we'd gone into the SEC, for example, the Division of
Corporation Finance, we got no action relief for some clients to say that, hey, our token
isn't a security.
Over the past four years, the door hasn't really been open for that sort of outreach
of the SEC.
It's good to hear that word again, though.
A lot in the industry have not heard that word in a while.
I know.
We're hopeful that with Atkins taking over next year, that that door will be open because
that dialogue with regulators, there's really no substitute for it.
Hearing what they're thinking and being able to candidly share what's going on in the industry
and what ideas seem directionally right, which ones don't, is important to good constructive
engagement between industry and regulators.
That makes a ton of sense.
Go ahead, Dan.
Yeah.
Where we've really excelled and grown has been in the area of these novel digital asset
requests and licensing issues.
And Josh is saying that's given us the ability to do a series of firsts, the first National
Trust Bank, some of the first chartering in New York and in other states, helping to get
approval for novel products.
And to do that, it's really understanding what is within the scope of permissible law,
but then also what is acceptable from a policy standpoint when you're working with a regulator.
Is it a new type of product or a new type of charter that as a policy matter, they want
to get involved with or have the personnel to supervise?
For some of the smaller state banking jurisdictions that do have state chartering regimes, very
often you're not going to get through the door on a novel request because they just
don't have the personnel or don't have the experience to have supervised specific products.
And then in talking to clients, it's also figuring out how do they see themselves?
Do they see themselves as a financial institution?
Do they see themselves as a tech company?
Very often the founders are technologists themselves and have developed really transformative
tech.
And that's a story that they want to tell.
It's a story that they're telling investors, and that becomes a story that they want to
tell regulators because they're rightfully proud of it.
But then it becomes a discussion with them about, well, the regulator, their mind's going
to go to what new risks does this bring up?
How are you solving for those risks?
What unintended consequences could this new technology or this new approval lead to?
You then have a discussion about transparency, which can then lead to a level of trust, which
then in turn leads to the ability to have a good solid working relationship that allows
for newer novel approvals as you build up that credibility in the state chartering space.
It's the type of thing that if you have good regulatory, solid regulatory supervisory history
that as the OCC opens up again, it allows for transferring those charters to the OCC
potentially.
It's this virtuous cycle that requires counseling, requires time, but we're really fortunate
that for many of our clients, these are multi-year engagements where we've seen them through
the highs and the lows and we can have that dialogue over time.
I would say it's an understatement to say that it has been a really difficult time to
operate a crypto business in the United States for the past few years and there's the normal
startup challenges, but then there's the murkiness in some areas, but also just the shifting
wins at some of these agencies and at some of these states where you're operating under
one set of assumptions for a few years and then an abrupt phase.
The OCC would be a good example there in terms of the chartering, but curious if there are
any lessons learned from helping some of these crypto companies get US approvals that translate
through various regimes, whether they be Democrat or Republican, or they're just some common
lessons.
A few lessons there might be, well, first of all, looking out for windows of opportunity
for when you can work quickly with regulators.
Over the past three to four years, as you mentioned, Matt, it's been a cloudy outlook
on the regulatory side in the US, but there are moments when, especially if there's leadership
changes at agencies, you can move quickly and you can get in and you can try to get
a new approval or a new charter.
Last time we saw that was in 2020 at the OCC.
There was a window where entities were able to go in and see charters and that window
closed.
I think one lesson there is you don't know when those windows will open.
You want to be prepared for when they do and have that be on your roadmap and to have all
your ducks in a row to be able to move when the opportunity is there and when it opens
to go move because you don't know when it's going to close, as we saw in 2021 with that
change in administration.
Then following up on a point Dana mentioned, having a roadmap important in tough times
For all the reasons that we just talked about, just to protect yourself if there's an aggressive
enforcement landscape, but it's also important moving into bull markets and being able to
make the transition because when deal opportunities come up and people are moving quickly and
trying to strike while the iron is hot, there is that increased risk of just getting out
over your skis and doing something that year, two years, three years down the line might
fall apart, might get criticized in a regulatory exam, might lead to lawsuits that could complicate
longer term business objectives like getting acquired or going public.
And we've seen that pass cycle where that overhang caused deals to not go through.
And it's something like, boy, if we had just stuck to the roadmap, stuck to the strategy,
we'd be in a better spot.
So I think that's one of the lessons learned is we're moving from winter into spring to
not lose sight of that roadmap.
And if anything, to bring it down and say, hey, what do we want to be focused on looking
into 2025 to make sure that we stay disciplined and we stay within our risk tolerance.
Yeah, I agree with all that.
And I think that these various strategies that work in those difficult regulatory engagements,
they're also things that lead to better outcomes in the context of M&A.
In the past year, we've touched eight different M&A projects, only three of which have ultimately
gone forward and the others fell to the wayside because of the diligence process and various
deal-based reasons.
The fact of the matter is, depending on the size of the acquirer, if it's a larger institution,
if it's an institution that doesn't have a similar level of risk tolerance, they may
not have the level of understanding of the uncertainty in the industry and choose to
say that's not something that they want to do.
So having those ducks in a row, as Josh was highlighting, that can unlock M&A, which I
think is going to be very big in the cycle.
The other thing would be difficult regulatory landscape, no doubt, taking a look at what
are some of the things that were put in place during the Biden administration that could
now potentially go away and unlock new opportunities.
So SAP 121 is an example.
If that goes away, you think you'll see more acquisition from banking entities.
How does risk tolerance align?
Those larger banking entities may want to see a cleaner history and if they're looking
at four or five different custodians, they're going to want to go with good tech, but then
they're also going to say which one has the most regulatory hair on it and that could
have you choose one over the other.
That makes sense.
I was going to ask you guys what some common pitfalls are in the bull market and it sounds
like buying something that you later regret would be high on the list.
Buying something you regret for different reasons.
One would be, does it have the regulatory hair on it?
So what are the outstanding obligations or issues with that and these regulators?
What's the scope of approvals that if you think you're acquiring an entity for a license,
what are the scope of approvals that exist and how difficult would that material change
process be to get the type of product, type of approval that you want in place?
Is this even a license that you need?
Is this an aqua hire?
How are these personnel going to work with your entity?
How are they going to be integrated?
How seamless is that going to be?
And entities can spend a lot of time, waste a lot of time trying to figure out who is
it that they're going to acquire and spend time on discussions and I think it's important
to ask that integration question right away.
It's more to ask, is this within the same scope of services that we need?
I think it's important to ask that question right away because, yes, it's a strong market
right now and there's a lot of funding going on, there's a lot of money out there, but
the clock is ticking.
Absolutely.
And I would add to that a few other pitfalls that might be in that securities area where
it's been such a friction point, obviously, the past few years, obviously, things may
lighten up a bit on the federal side, at least from an enforcement standpoint, but that doesn't
mean that laws still don't apply.
You have the laws on all the books and especially on the state level where, at least we saw
on the last cycle, state AGs would come up and still remain active.
I think we can expect to see that, especially in the democratic-leaning states if they perceive
that there is any sort of enforcement void being left at the federal level, that states
like New York, others may step in and try to fill that.
So if you're a crypto company and thinking, boy, I could just clearly open up, there still
are a lot of things to keep an eye out for and, again, just reiterating the importance
sticking to that roadmap, launching stuff that really works, that is usable, that's compliant
with those long-standing principles, at least until you get a federal law in place, I know
we're going to touch on this later, that could help clarify market structure issues.
Still important to keep those fundamental principles in view.
That makes sense.
In that regard, I think another really important area is you can feel it's loosening up, you
can feel perhaps a more permissive environment and legislation that's forthcoming, but there
are going to be aspects of the law that, if they're not enforced, have a very long tail
on them.
So one thing that comes to mind is OFAC and the sanctions compliance.
So you've got a borderless technology, we have entities that are working active all
over the world.
Even if enforcement in the sanctions area went away or diminished over the course of
the next couple of years, there's a 10-year statute of limitations on bank fraud in the
sanctions arena.
So you could have a good environment right now, but you could still, if you don't have
proper controls in place, you could still be engaged in activity that down the line
could either have unintended consequences or have enforcement.
And I'm back to the M&A idea.
Those are the types of questions that I think sophisticated participants are going to ask.
The travel rule compliance thing is just baffling to me that some folks still aren't in compliance
with the travel rule.
I feel like we were talking about that in 2013 and the technology exists to become compliant.
I'm very surprised that the market structure has not evolved there.
I don't think people think of it.
It's core to U.S. foreign policy, the idea of slavery of economic warfare.
It goes back to the War of 1812, the idea of imposing sanctions.
It's not going to go away.
And in the early 2011, 2012, 2013, there was a whole slew of enforcement against larger
banking institutions, billions of dollars in penalties that were imposed.
I think that that is something that, down the line, we're going to see more of in this
area.
But you're right.
That has been a perennial issue.
Yeah.
And strict liability, too, if I'm not mistaken.
Sanctions, absolutely.
And I think part of the issues there, I think, matter just to make sure these around rule
making, involving the travel rule, I think, since it had a proposed rule out for a long
period of time around how unhosted walls can be treated.
And I think industry is waiting to see how some of those initiatives land, but completely
agreed regarding the need to just get structure in place that complies using some of those
industry bodies that have been working hard to put stuff that works in place.
And even if it doesn't line up exactly with where the end regulations are, you could true
it up later.
And it also just helps protect you, your software, your business from being used by bad actors.
That's a thing that we see time and again.
It's like, well, you may have arguments that what you're doing doesn't trip these requirements.
But if you have the bad luck of having your product be the one that's the favored means
for North Korea to fund its nuclear program, the government has a lot of breath in under
these laws to try to come after somebody and to find a throat to choke.
So it's just all the more important to make sure that you're doing what you can to have
a good reasonable program around those issues.
And as we're in this, call it maybe like first wave of tokenization, we've got projects around
tokenized money markets, ETFs, stable coins, tokenized deposits, tokenized bonds, as you
start having tokenized versions of these vehicles that are then traveling around globally.
If you don't have those controls in place, you're just potentially baking in problems
down the road.
And every government body, every regulator views the world through their own jurisdictional
lens.
And I think the industry has been really focused on because of just the level of enforcement
has been focused on the SEC and securities compliance and enforcement activity there.
But it's just only one part of a comprehensive view of the world.
Yeah, that's spot on.
So I'd love to talk a little bit about what 2025 and beyond is going to look like here
from a US regulatory landscape.
And maybe the first thing on the docket is stable coins.
So if we just look at within our portfolio where the most growth is, I'd say it's in
the stable coin category.
Some of these businesses are just growing faster than probably any business in the history
of crypto, which is the demand for dollars internationally seems to be insatiable.
And if you look on chain, I think some days 70% of every blockchain transaction is a stable
coin transaction.
So it's very clear we need something here.
Seems like it's a priority.
Franchillo said it's a first 100 day type of priority.
But what would a stable coin bill look like from your guys' perspective?
So agreed.
It's been a very, very fast growing area.
And I think for good reason.
It really is a killer app for blockchain, having dollar value that can be transferred
instantaneously.
A lot of real good notified use cases for it.
And it's also an area, one of those rare areas where you're seeing bipartisan consensus
that you need some federal legislation around this market.
And what we're seeing among the different bills that have been put out there are a few
trends, a few commonalities.
One is it looks like Congress is trying to leverage and learn from the leadership that
the New York DFS had demonstrated by getting out there early and setting forth robust standards
for what the reserves need to consist of very safe short-term cash equivalents effectively.
You need to have clear redemption commitments, you need to have transparency to the reserves
and a means of auditing them so people can have faith that the reserves are actually
there.
Those time-tested protections we've seen DFS apply appear to be in most of these bills,
which we think is a good thing.
And I think it's a testament to states being the laboratories of democracy and really proving
this out.
But there's also areas where states just don't have the power to legislate and enforce other
necessary aspects for this inherently cross-border activity.
Some of those are clarifying and just confirming the bankruptcy remote treatment of stablecoin
reserves, formalizing ways for US regulators to coordinate with international regulators
because it's not just something that happens interstate, but it's also something where
there's very much a global market to this and you need those coordination mechanisms.
But really recognizing that stablecoin activity requires some form of bank or bank-like regulation.
It doesn't have to be a full-service bank like an insured depository institution, but
to have that capital requirements, supervision, examination, something at that level of that
New York trust company or charters like that, if there's a federal option, I think that's
something that we're seeing in all these bills and it seems to make sense for the industry
as well.
Yeah, I think the states need to continue to play a role.
I think that the dual banking system has worked well, especially with the states being the
And the fact is, with the DFS guidance and with a substantial amount of time in the market
supervising these entities there, there are a lot of really good lessons learned.
I think that there are and should be roles for both state and federal regulators there,
but then it's borderless.
So the maker regime, obviously, you have stablecoins that are being issued out of Singapore.
You've got inconsistent approaches to things like reserve management.
You have potentially consistent approaches that could impact the bankruptcy remoteness
of reserves.
These are all, I think, things that need to be worked through.
Stablecoins have that initial market because you've got billions of people in places where
they're worried about the value of their money, they're worried about hyperinflation, they're
worried about devaluation of their currency, they don't trust their own banking systems.
So yeah, they're turning to stablecoins.
You've got companies that are a part of that ecosystem because of the yield that can be
generated from those reserve assets.
But I think in order for it to grow in scale, it probably needs to go beyond that payment
bridge currency type of offering.
We don't know what's going to happen with interest rates.
So what happens with a stablecoin in a lower zero interest rate environment, which that
could potentially happen.
So I think the next thing to look out for would be stablecoins that either are things
like white label platforms that stablecoins are issued with partners, stablecoins that
are issued in tandem with assets that are on chain.
So I think the tokenization area is that scales, you'll probably have more market opportunities
for stablecoins.
Key areas around things like payments and payroll and card services, having all those
integrated in the stablecoin ecosystem, those are all the types of things that I think are
going to facilitate growth.
Just thinking back past market cycles and the failures in governance, the frauds that
I've hit like garden variety fraud, I think you're going to see that same thing go up
somewhere here in this cycle.
If that activity happens in the stablecoin space with unregulated issuers, for example,
I think that's the kind of thing that could cause regulators, lawmakers to react negatively
and then the pendulum swings in the other direction.
So that's another thing to look out for.
But I think that this is probably the application of this market cycle and probably has some
of the most promise.
Banking relationships though need to probably loosen up.
Right now there are very few, but I think as those providers grow, as the use cases
grow, this is probably the killer use case of the cycle.
Well, I hope you're right about preserving the state pathway because I look at the bill
where it says $10 billion asset cap and that seems really low to me.
That would be a very small stablecoin issuer and you need to look back on this past cycle,
there really wasn't a federal pathway.
So it makes it tricky.
Yeah.
It obviously depends which of these bills ended up becoming the leading horse, but I
think the Hickory bill would have provided an option for the appropriate federal regulator
to allow the state issuers to remain under state supervision, but I agree that may not
be strong enough for those who want to remain under that state system.
And I think one of the important design questions that may create the political space for that
compromise to allow a more entrenched and viable state option in this space would be,
how do we deal with the risk that there is a failed stablecoin issuer at scale?
Because this market is getting massive and already one of the largest markets for treasuries
in the world.
And especially if we move into a macroeconomic climate where certain other purchasers of
treasuries aren't buying as many, well, this could be a way to sponge up some of that decreased
demand and really become an instrument of economic and fiscal policy in a way.
But that brings in bigger central bank type questions about what protections do you have
there.
So certain bills, I believe Lummis-Chilagrand had a mechanism where the FDIC might step
in as receivers.
So you put that full bank receivership protection behind it.
Other bills have provided mechanisms for reserves to be pledged so you could get access to
liquidity so you don't have to engage in a fire sale of those treasuries.
But our hope is as people really start getting into the brass tacks and finishing up these
bills, there's a lot more attention given to those mechanisms because if those could
be applied uniformly across state and federal issuers, you could then have that foundation
to have the comfort to allow state issuers to remain that and they don't have to convert
to federal issuers.
Much in the same way that we have state chartered insured depository institutions, they don't
have to convert to becoming national banks at a certain point because there is a sufficient
degree of federal oversight and involvement with what they're doing.
Yeah, you guys must deal with some interesting companies because you could imagine a world
where it's, hey, congratulations on your stable coin company.
Here's your SIFI designation.
Your whole business is now a SIFI.
Yeah, the treasury's FSOC has still been being that drama saying we may use these tools over
the past few years.
They haven't to date, but that's one wild card that's out there.
So I would say that the holy grail for a lot of entrepreneurs has been a market structure
bill that would give clarity around securities versus commodities and how the spot market
should operate around both of these.
Tokenized securities at scale aren't even a thing yet really in this industry.
They're really just on the margin and obviously a lot of cryptocurrencies out there have been
accused of being an unregistered security by this SEC.
So I guess the question is, do we get a market structure bill and also are there just some
things the SEC could do here in 2025 that would answer some of these questions in advance
of a market structure bill?
All good questions.
I think first of all, the stable coin bill is probably the lower hanging fruit.
That's the one that we're hearing will probably move first.
Market structure is just harder.
There are just a lot of different constituents and really difficult legal issues.
In terms of what the SEC could do out of the gate, they could issue more precise guidance
around steps and principles that issuers could take that would presently put them outside
the scope of securities registration requirements that had been done in the past.
The SEC gave some guidance in 2019, but it was very just here a bunch of principles and
it wasn't clear to industry and counsel which ones mattered most and how they fit together.
So guidance that would be more around here particular models that could work if done
in this particular way.
And what I'm thinking of in particular, some of the 2016-17 era network token launches
that were really focused on use and having real use right out of the gate, selling tokens
more as a beta software, they're not committing to developing using funds to develop them
more.
So you cut off this theory that they were really a failed fundraising instrument and
lay out a model like that.
For there to be any broad systematic fix and approach, you would need legislation for that,
especially if it's something that we need to supplant or clarify parts of the Howie test
because that's a judge-made doctrine.
And even if the SEC isn't enforcing certain aspects of that, it wouldn't stop private
plaintiffs from going in and bringing suits.
So you really do need a federal law to create a clear pathway for governance token issuers
that are going to be centralized for some period of time, there may be a need for disclosure
for some period of time until they reach a sufficient degree of decentralization.
And then at some later point, just like Ethereum did, moved to a point where it was really
just a commodity because there was no material information that Insider would have that would
be relevant to somebody deciding whether to hold or sell the token.
Yeah.
And I think that disparities are always going to exist in terms of approach.
Even if we got a market structure bill in place in the US, it then becomes, okay, how
will each of these bodies go about implementing their various mandates?
So it would be good because the uncertainty around enforcement gets diminished as that
specter goes away.
And then you move into like, what is day-to-day life like?
Do those bodies have people in place that are sufficiently on top of the topic that
they know the questions to ask and you don't fall in this never-ending cycle of back and
forth?
The people become the policy at a certain point.
So I think that market structure bill needs to go along with what is the funding, is there
money to pay these people so that they can be in seat and take these jobs on?
But then even if you have that in the US, then I think you still have regional disparities
between US and non-US players.
I think the US probably always running towards the higher side of the bar.
So I think getting rid of the uncertainty around the specter of enforcement, I hope
that does a lot.
But red lag is a thing and there's always going to be a certain level of uncertainty.
And when you're interacting with these various government bodies, also the point about funding
and personnel, are they in the spot where they know what questions to ask, where they
know how to quantify the risk?
Probably a really good time to be an M&A lawyer with this market structure bill potentially
coming because if you just look at all the banks and the broker dealers out there and
how many of them are actually in this space, it's very few and it's probably for these
reasons.
Absolutely.
And we're seeing, obviously, the past month with the election results, entities that just
haven't had a crypto strategy coming back say, well, we need to revisit this.
We need to see should we have a strategy in this space and is it really time to build
organically or at this point do we need to acquire?
Do we need to get something, go out and get an existing proven market participant?
And as Dana mentioned earlier, in addition to the market structure clarity, I think clearing
up that staff accounting bullet 121 around treatment of custodial crypto, that's a real
niche issue, but it was a huge blocker.
It's been a huge blocker to banks being in the market to acquire custodians or even to
custody assets under their own umbrella because you had to book custody crypto as a safekeeping
liability.
And for ordinary corporations, that's something that's annoying, but they found a way to deal
with it.
For banks, you've got statutory capital requirements and it just would really create friction around
that.
So if that is to decide, then I think we could really see M&A open up on that front too.
And that could directly be day one where staff 121 goes away.
Exactly.
That's been something that's been a real blocker towards the regular institutions wanting
to jump in or being able to jump in.
So outside of market structure and the obvious, hey, banks are coming to the market, broker
dealers are coming in, we're going to see technology companies coming in.
Are there any other categories of just broader capital markets that you expect to start to
penetrate into this industry?
So I don't know how much it's going to penetrate the industry because it's moving very slow
and it's a risk adverse industry.
But I think that there is a real role to be played by insurance companies in helping to
create frameworks for what should be put in place from a safety and soundness standpoint.
What should regulators look for in approving licensing to products where they don't know
how to quantify the risk?
So the thing I keep thinking about is there were really no building codes up until there
were some rudimentary ones.
But in the 1800s, you had people that were representing the fire insurance industry that
lost huge sums of money at various city fires that then sat down and said, okay, well, here's
what a modern building code should look like.
And they helped develop the model building code that was replicated in a lot of different
jurisdictions. I think there's something like that here where you have novel technology
that somebody needs to come in and say, if you have this, this, and this place, here
would be our willingness to ensure something like a profit-involved bridging, or here's
what we need to be in place in order for us to insure a custodial product.
Insurance companies, they are entities that have real financial skin in the game and
could help set expectations that could be replicated by regulators and lawmakers and
lead to further clarity, streamlining things for the industry.
That's a really out of the box answer to that question.
I was not expecting it to go that direction, but I think you know our insurance guy, so
he's going to be really happy to hear you say that, Dana, but it makes a ton of sense.
That's how you probably get some clarity on how you should be running certain custody
schemes, even on the inside of a big bank.
That's right, because if you're an outside party that's got money that's at risk and
they are willing to insure a product from failure one, we've got consumers that could
potentially recover from something like that, but it could give lawmakers, it could give
regulators a place to start.
We're also seeing seeds of that being used already in the custodial space where trying
to persuade regulators, hey, this new custodial technology is something that's safe and
sound, it's something that should be approvable.
Well, the regulators often don't have that native expertise to go test that stuff
themselves, so they'll want to say, well, is there a third party that's got skin in the
game? Like Dana's saying, who's willing to put their money behind that proposition?
Well, insurance company would be one of those.
So they see what insurers want to insure this technology at the same rate that they
would the legacy one.
That's a helpful data point, getting your custody technology approved.
So we just spent 10 years trying to get the banks and the broker dealer CEOs on board.
Now we've got to think about the insurance company CEOs.
Might take a while. Guys, this has been great.
Really appreciate you giving us the lay of the land in terms of where this industry is
going. Where can we send people that want to learn more about your practice?
Paul Hastings dot com.
You can see Josh and I, our bios, you can reach out to us on LinkedIn as well.
Awesome. All right, guys, really appreciate it coming on.
Thanks, Matt. Thank you.
Thanks for listening to another episode of On the Brink with Castle Island.
To find out more about Castle Island, visit Castle Island dot V.C.
To listen to all of our podcast episodes, please go to on the brink dash podcast dot
com or just click on the tab in our website.
Thanks for listening.